what is up guys in this video i'm going
to be showing you how you can get
started with python
in less than 10 minutes and i'm going to
be using python 3.8 for this
along with pycharm as my code editor
you can just search these on google and
they will pop up immediately
they are free and open source so
definitely do check those out
otherwise let's get started immediately
with the first thing you should know in
python and that is how to assign values
to
variables so to create a variable all
you have to do is decide on a name such
as
item and then you can just assign it a
value
this is a string and a string is just
any form of text
for the program to read and you also
need to keep in mind
that python is a case sensitive language
which means item with a small
i and item with a big i are going to
mean
absolutely different things and also a
naming convention
in python is to add an underscore every
time you have more than one word
so if we say item name you want to add
this underscore over here
and we can just say orange so now we
have a few strings assigned
to three different variables let's go
ahead and print
first the difference between item and
item just to show you
that there is a difference so we'll go
ahead and click on run
and you'll notice it will say banana and
apple
now let's go ahead and print another
string which this time is going to be
hello
and we're going to add a plus and
the item name so as you can see we can
actually combine text and when we print
that it's going to say hello orange
next we have data types so the first one
is the integer which is just any number
and you're going to notice it being
written
in blue then we have strings which as i
showed you earlier is just any text
inside quotation marks then we have
booleans which is just a simple
true or false so as you can see we can
just type in false here
or true here and that's all that it is
it just says true or false
and the final one you should know for
getting started
is list which all you have to do is
create a pair of angle brackets
and insert the values you want inside
here and it can be a mixture between
numbers booleans and so on but for this
example we'll just keep it simple
and write a few strings then if we go
ahead and print these
you're going to notice that we will get
2021 text
false and the list but let's move on to
an example that we want to print these
values
combined so let's say name is mario the
string
number is going to equal 22. so you're
going to notice 2021
is a blue number and this one is green
because this is considered text while
this is considered
an integer so what we need to do is
actually convert them into the correct
types before combining them
so to do that we can just go ahead and
type in print name plus
the string value of integer so it's
going to convert the integer to a string
so that we can combine these two texts
together if we remove that
and only write integer you're going to
notice we are going to get an exception
that says we cannot do that
and the same thing goes for the string
number pretend we want to add the value
of 10 to the string number the editor
will be nice enough to tell you you
shouldn't do that
and we should just put some parentheses
there and type in
in ahead of that so we can convert it to
an integer and add it easily
next let's move on to math so we will
create two variables one will be
10 and one will be five and to do math
in python
it's very self-explanatory as you can
see to do addition you just need to add
a plus symbol
for the difference you just add a minus
symbol to multiply you add an
asterisk to divide you add a slash and
if you want the exponential power
just add two asterisks and you'll notice
that if we print all of these
you're going to get a very quick
calculator so of course 10 plus 5 is 15
a minus b is going to be 5 and so on you
will get the values that correspond
to those operators okay next let's go
ahead
and create a logic statement so we're
going to use
these two values so is happy is false
age is 28.
let's pretend we want something to
happen if the age is more than 21
we'll say print you are old and if they
are not old
we can also type in l if the age
is equal to 18 we will tell them you are
getting old
and if it's neither of those we can go
ahead and say
you are still young and the same thing
goes with the
is happy statement so we type in if the
person is happy
we can write you are happy else they are
probably not happy
so we will just write you are not happy
and when we play it it's going to say
they are not happy because is happy
is false and if we set this to true it's
going to change to
you are happy so the if statement just
takes into account whether a statement
is true or
false and depending on that it's going
to give the outcome of the values
and the if else statement is going to
probably be your most
used logic next let's move on to the for
loop
so for i in range of three which means
it's going to
loop over three values we want to print
hello and we can add a comma here
and the value of i so if we print this
you're going to notice
it's going to say hello0 hello1 hello2
because
in programming the index always starts
at 0.
so if you actually want that to start at
one you're going to have to manually add
one
to i so now you get hello one hello to
hello three
and also just so you know what range is
we can go down here
and we can go ahead and type in print
range
of three so you're going to notice it's
going to create a range object which is
going to have the values from 0
to 3 so this can iterate three times
over that but you should also know
that this works for lists so we can
create a name list
and we can type in for name in name list
we can print the name next we have a
while loop so we're just gonna type in i
equals zero and while i is less than
five
we're going to increment the value of i
by one
each time it goes in this loop and
finally we want to print the value of i
so what you should get
are five values printed out just like
this because as soon as this statement
becomes false
it's going to exit out of this loop and
just terminate the program but a reason
to use this is because you can create an
infinite loop such as while true and
that's never going to be false and
inside here we're going to type in
user input and that's going to equal an
input
that says enter something and if
the user input is equal to the string of
zero then we're going to print we are
done here
and we are also going to break
and what break does is just cancel the
loop which means
if we type in zero this loop is no
longer going to be valid
and it's going to exit out of the
program otherwise it's going to loop
forever and if we actually play the
program you're going to notice that
finally we can add some inputs so we can
type in 10
we can do two we can type in whatever
that is
but as soon as we type in zero it's
going to exit the loop because
it will reach this break statement and
the program will finish
moving on to functions to create a
function
all you have to do is use the def
keyword and just name the function
however you like of course i'm going to
use
the underscore naming convention and
this function is only going to be used
to say hello to the user so
here we can go ahead and type in print
hey there and we're going to insert the
name so you might be wondering
what are functions and what do we use
functions for well functions are just
used to
reuse your code in many different
instances because
the main point of programming is to
reuse your code
as much as possible you want to maximize
how often you can
reuse the same line of code without
having to rewrite it
so for example now we created a function
that says hello we can type in mario
and we can also use it again and we can
type in luigi and when we run the
program it will say hey there mario
and hey there luigi instead of writing
this statement
twice we were able to just use one
function to do it multiple times
and one thing we should cover also on
functions is pretend you have
a lot of functions you need to create
such as get
internet and run game something
such as that and you don't really have
the logic for it yet so you're going to
notice that these
are empty if you run the program you're
going to get
an error but python has created this
keyword that is called pass
which essentially just says there's
nothing in here we accept that
and your program is still going to be
able to run regardless of having no
content inside the function now when we
tap on run you're going to notice there
are going to be
no errors because the program's going to
understand that we provided the keyword
pass
which just tells it that there's nothing
there and it accepts it but this is very
good for creating the blueprints later
in case you need to write everything
your program should do but don't really
know how to do that yet
just insert the word pass and it will
save you a lot of trouble
and finally we're going to go over how
we can use the try
and accept block so for here we're going
to create an
input and it's going to say please
provide
a number so now we're going to go ahead
and type in try
and we're going to try to print the
value plus the
integer of the number that we get from
the user
and if that doesn't work we're going to
print that
that is not a valid number
so the way it works is it tries to
execute the code that's inside here
and if anything goes wrong if an
exception occurs it's going to go
to the accept block and it's going to
execute whatever is inside that
of course if you write something that
throws an exception inside here
you need to try with another try and
accept block but if we go ahead and run
the program now we can write something
like 10
and it's going to add 10 to the value
but of course what if we write something
such as mario
try adding mario to 10 and the program
is not going to be happy
because you cannot convert mario to an
integer and then add it to 10. so it's
going to say
you shouldn't do that but don't worry
because we have the exception covered
and our program will say that is not a
valid number and not throw an exception
but anyway
i really hope that helped you to get
started with python of course there's a
lot more to cover
this was just meant as a very quick
guide for helping you to get started
and with that being said have a
wonderful day and i'll see you guys in
the next video